<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Fediverse on BadgeFed Official Blog</title>
    <link>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/tags/fediverse/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fediverse on BadgeFed Official Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 16:27:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/tags/fediverse/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>BadgeFed: From Prototype to Reality</title>
      <link>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/post/02-roadmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 16:27:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/post/02-roadmap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey Fediverse, we&amp;rsquo;ve got some exciting news—BadgeFed is moving out of the prototype phase! That&amp;rsquo;s right, what started as a scrappy proof-of-concept is now becoming a real, structured, and (dare we say) polished federated badge system.
And since we believe in working out in the open, we want to share our roadmap with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-big-three-priorities-&#34;&gt;The Big Three Priorities 🏆&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re focusing on three major areas to take BadgeFed from &amp;ldquo;hey, this kinda works&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;oh wow, this is actually usable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hey Fediverse, we&rsquo;ve got some exciting news—BadgeFed is moving out of the prototype phase! That&rsquo;s right, what started as a scrappy proof-of-concept is now becoming a real, structured, and (dare we say) polished federated badge system.
And since we believe in working out in the open, we want to share our roadmap with you.</p>
<h2 id="the-big-three-priorities-">The Big Three Priorities 🏆</h2>
<p>We&rsquo;re focusing on three major areas to take BadgeFed from &ldquo;hey, this kinda works&rdquo; to &ldquo;oh wow, this is actually usable.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="1-authentication-">1. Authentication 🔐</h3>
<p>Right now, logging in is a bit of a mess. So we&rsquo;re tackling authentication properly, integrating OAuth so you can log in using your Mastodon (or other Fediverse) account.
We&rsquo;re building this with .NET and Blazor because performance and scalability matter. Plus, no one wants to manage yet another username/password combo.</p>
<h3 id="2-federation--spec-">2. Federation &amp; Spec 🌍</h3>
<p>We&rsquo;re making sure BadgeFed speaks ActivityPub fluently. Right now, federation kinda-sorta works, but we need to define a proper spec that makes badge issuing,
earning, and verification seamless across different platforms. Whether you&rsquo;re on Mastodon, Pleroma, or something else entirely, BadgeFed should just work.
We&rsquo;re ironing out the kinks so badges travel as smoothly as your cat pictures. Also we want to support export and import from OpenBadges spec, and we need to do some experimentation on how this could travel on the fediverse.</p>
<h3 id="3-packaging-docs-and-docker-">3. Packaging, Docs, and Docker 📦</h3>
<p>What&rsquo;s cooler than a decentralized badge system? A decentralized badge system that&rsquo;s easy to set up.
We&rsquo;re working on clear documentation, making installation painless, and putting together a Docker container so you don&rsquo;t have to wrestle with dependencies or even dotnet.
One command, and boom—you&rsquo;re federating badges like a pro.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="the-would-be-nice-priorities-">The &ldquo;Would Be Nice&rdquo; Priorities ✨</h2>
<p>Once the big three are solid, we&rsquo;re setting our sights on some much-needed improvements:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Approval Process &amp; Expiration</strong> – Not all badges should last forever. We&rsquo;re adding controls for expiration dates and approval workflows.</li>
<li><strong>Stats &amp; Insights</strong> – Want to see how many people are earning badges? We&rsquo;ll be adding analytics to track adoption and engagement.</li>
<li><strong>CSS &amp; UI/UX Love</strong> – Let&rsquo;s be honest, the prototype is functional, but it&rsquo;s not winning any beauty contests. Expect smoother UI, better mobile support, and fewer &ldquo;why is this button here?&rdquo; moments.</li>
<li><strong>Landing Page</strong> – BadgeFed deserves a proper introduction. A clean, informative landing page is in the works.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="whats-next-">What&rsquo;s Next? 📅</h2>
<p>We&rsquo;re heads-down working on these priorities, but as always, feedback, ideas, and contributions are welcome.
This is an open-source project, and the best way to make sure it fits the needs of the Fediverse is to have the community involved.</p>
<p>If you want to help, hop into our discussions, check out the repo at <a href="https://github.com/tryvocalcat/badgefed">https://github.com/tryvocalcat/badgefed</a>, or just share your thoughts. Let&rsquo;s make federated badges a thing! 🏅</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing a Minimalistic ActivityPub Badge System: Decentralized, Verified, and Built for the Fediverse</title>
      <link>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/post/01-init/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 20:27:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/post/01-init/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the ever-evolving world of digital credentials, we’ve seen centralized platforms like Credly dominate the badge and certification space.
But what if we could flip the script? What if badges could be decentralized, self-certified, and issued directly by organizations in the Fediverse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reusing the social graph already present in the Fediverse, we can enable a seamless integration of badges into the networks people are already part of.
Instead of creating new, siloed systems for certification, we can utilize the trusted connections and relationships within platforms like Mastodon to issue and verify badges.
It’s about making the credentialing process as decentralized and open as the social interactions we have online today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the ever-evolving world of digital credentials, we’ve seen centralized platforms like Credly dominate the badge and certification space.
But what if we could flip the script? What if badges could be decentralized, self-certified, and issued directly by organizations in the Fediverse?</p>
<p>By reusing the social graph already present in the Fediverse, we can enable a seamless integration of badges into the networks people are already part of.
Instead of creating new, siloed systems for certification, we can utilize the trusted connections and relationships within platforms like Mastodon to issue and verify badges.
It’s about making the credentialing process as decentralized and open as the social interactions we have online today.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s exactly what I&rsquo;m working on with my latest project: a minimalistic ActivityPub implementation for badges, built using #dotnet.</p>
<h2 id="the-problem-with-traditional-badge-systems">The Problem with Traditional Badge Systems</h2>
<p>It’s mind-blowing that major organizations—think Microsoft, Non-Profits, and educational institutions—spend thousands of dollars on badge providers like Pearson just to get a &ldquo;verified&rdquo; badge.
These badges, while useful, are locked into centralized platforms that limit the potential for genuine, open verification systems.</p>
<p>What if badges could be as decentralized as social media profiles? Imagine organizations running their own badge systems—similar to the way social media instances like Mastodon operate in the Fediverse.
Think about a domain-based badge system like <code>badges.mozilla.com</code>, or a school district offering badges at <code>certifications.myschooldistrict.com</code>. Even a podcast could issue badges to its guests, with the entire verification happening directly within the domain.</p>
<h2 id="why-activitypub">Why ActivityPub?</h2>
<p>ActivityPub is already a powerful protocol for secure, decentralized communication between actors in the Fediverse.
It enables us to create verifiable interactions and sign digital artifacts in a way that was previously the domain of a few centralized certificate authorities.
With ActivityPub, we can extend this to badges, allowing people and organizations to interact with verified credentials in the same decentralized way that we share posts,
follows, and interactions across Mastodon or any other Fediverse platform.</p>
<p>Think about how LetsEncrypt disrupted the centralized SSL certificate market. Now, with a decentralized badge system, we can enable a similar revolution for verified credentials.</p>
<h2 id="the-project-so-far">The Project So Far</h2>
<p>I’ve made some solid progress, and there’s now a functional proof of concept (PoC) in place. The project is live and can be found here: <a href="https://github.com/tryvocalcat/activitypub-badges">ActivityPub Badges on GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>This fediverse actor, the badges issuer, isn’t a Mastodon instance, a Pleroma, or a blog—it’s an actor in a badge system. You can follow it on Mastodon, but its badges are not microblogging notes.
Instead, think of it as a way to display verified credentials directly from a decentralized source.</p>
<p>Here’s the first badge I’ve issued:</p>
<p><a href="https://badges.vocalcat.com/record/10">First Badge: View on Mastodon</a></p>
<p>Simply copy and paste the URL and open it in your Mastodon client. The badge will show up as a note, and you can celebrate, comment, or share it within your ActivityPub network.
This is how the badge system will work—just like social media, but with credentials!</p>
<h2 id="a-decentralized-future-for-badges">A Decentralized Future for Badges</h2>
<p>The ultimate goal is to create a decentralized badge system where different instances of badge issuers will recognize each other’s certifications.
This way, even if a certificate issuer disappears, the credential is still secure and verifiable across the network.
Imagine the survivability of certificates in such a system—if your issuer disappears, the credential still exists in a federated, decentralized space.</p>
<p>It’s an exciting future, and I’m just getting started. If you want to learn more about the progress of this project, follow me, or check out the GitHub repo. (Btw, I am not a Mastodon account, or a BadgeFed system, I am a static site).</p>
<p>Let’s create a future where verification is decentralized, secure, and open for everyone.</p>
<h2 id="early-adopter-badge-who-wants-one">Early Adopter Badge: Who Wants One?</h2>
<p>As with any new project, there’s always room for early adopters. If you’re interested in getting your own badge, let me know! Follow the progress and get involved as we continue to build this decentralized badge system.</p>
<hr>
<p>Feel free to share your thoughts, questions, and comments. Badge up, own your credentials, and let the Fediverse showcase your achievements.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello Fediverse!</title>
      <link>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/post/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 18:27:54 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://badgefed.vocalcat.com/post/hello-world/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
